Finding aid for the Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres collection, 1985-1991 LSC.1848
UCLA Library Special Collections
Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres collection
1985-1991
UCLA Library Special Collections
Connexxus (Center)
LSC.1848
11.5 linear feet (16 boxes)
The Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres Collection contains the administrative records of Connexxus / Centro de Mujeres, one of the first Los Angeles non-profit organizations that catered and provided services to lesbians.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9966506283606533
Historical Note
Historical note (version 2) by Tiffany-Kay Sangwand
In early 1984, Adel Martinez and Lauren Jardine conceived the idea behind Connexxus, a women-run center in Los Angeles that provides quality and comprehensive services that cater to women, particularly lesbians. In May 1984, Martinez, Jardine, and a group of women met in the home of Vivian Brown to discuss the idea and how to bring it into fruition. They envisioned a space in which lesbians could thrive professionally, personally, and socially.
In January 1985, Connexxus opened its doors on Santa Monica Boulevard in West Hollywood. Connexxus' initial space was a 1400 square foot facility with ten rooms which served as a space for a library, workshops, rap groups, counseling, meetings, and other social activities. Lauren Jardine, Ph.D. was hired as the Executive Director. Connexxus operated under the non-profit auspices of Southern California Women for Understanding until receiving its own 501(c)(3) non-profit organization status in July 1985.
Connexxus operated for six years out of West Hollywood. In 1986, it opened Connexxus East / Centro de Mujeres, a satellite location in East Los Angeles. Connexxus offered a variety of services at its two locations including referrals, support groups, the Alliance (Connexxus Business and Professional Women's Alliance), the West Coast Lesbian Collection / June Mazer Lesbian Archive, counseling / therapy services, workshops, social events, and a coffeehouse. Connexxus East specifically did outreach to Latina lesbians in East L.A. Connexxus also collaborated with a number of other non-profit organizations in Los Angeles, such as Southern California Women for Understanding (SCWU), Alcoholism Center for Women (ACW), and Lesbian Central at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center (currently the L.A. Gay and Lesbian Center).
At its peak, Connexxus operated on a budget of over $200,000, which was anomalous among grassroots lesbian organizations at the time. Their funding was made possible from the City of West Hollywood, donations from the women who utilized its services and gay men who were allies.
When Connexxus opened, it filled the vacuum for a women / lesbian public space in Los Angeles. During its six years of operation, other specialized organizations and businesses emerged to serve the dynamic Los Angeles lesbian population. This was reflected in a decline of Connexxus users; in 1990 Connexxus decided to cease operations. Two of its programs, the June Mazer Lesbian Archive and Connexxus East, remained open and operated independently after Connexxus' closing.
Historical note (version 1) by Joy Novak
In 1984, a group of lesbian activists led by Del Martínez and Lauren Jardine founded Connexxus Women's Center/Centro de Mujeres. Connexxus was first located on Santa Monica Boulevard and later on La Cienega Boulevard in West Hollywood. At its peak, Connexxus operated on a budget of over $200,00, which was unheard of in grassroots lesbian organizations.
Connexxus programs included referrals, a variety of supports groups, a business alliance, mental health services, workshops, social events, dances and a program for Latina lesbians in East Los Angeles. Connexxus also co-sponsored the first Latina Lesbian Mental Health Conference in 1986. In 1987 Connexxus took over the management of the West Coast Lesbian Collection, which was moved from Oakland and was renamed the June Mazer Lesbian Archive.
Connexxus collaborated with other community groups such as SCWU (Southern California Women for Understanding), ACW (Alcoholism Center for Women) and Lesbian Central at the Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center (now the L.A. Gay and Lesbian Center). Connexxus closed in 1990.
Chronology
Missing Title
May 1984 First meeting led by Lauren Jardine and Adel Martinez to discuss the idea of Connexxus.
January 1985 Connexxus opens its doors on 9054 Santa Monica Boulevard in West Hollywood.
June 1985 First Board of Directors meeting with Carol Anderson, Beverly Cook, Jeanne Cordova, Sue Dell, Adel Martinez, June Mazer, Anne Mosbergen, Pat Pimentel, Carol Przbycien, Terry Scannell, Pepper Sheaffer, Sharon Siegel, Karen Sterling, Linda Wineland and Judith Wright. Adel Martinez served as the first Board President.
July 1985 Connexxus gains 501(c)(3) non-profit organization status.
July 1985 Counseling / therapy services first offered.
September 1985 Receives grant from the National Endowment for the Arts and the California Arts Council to host writer and performance artist, Terry Wolverton, as an artist-in-residence.
November 1985 The Alliance (Connexxus Business and Professional Women's Alliance, CBPWA) holds its first meeting.
Februrary 1986 Connexxus Connects Us, a documentary on Connexxus airs on Falcon Cable television.
May 1986 Connexxus Latina lesbian rap groups meet at El Centro in East Los Angeles.
October 1986 Connexxus purchases Bunches of Balloons, a for-profit business as part of its Economic Empowerment Project.
November 1986 Connexxus co-sponsors Latina Lesbian Mental Health Conference
December 1986 Connexxus adopts West Coast Lesbian Collections
January 1987 Connexxus co-sponsors Boundary Dilemmas in the Client-Therapist Relationship: A Working Conference for Lesbian Therapists
January 15, 1987 Board member June Mazer passes away due to cancer
April 1987 The June Mazer Lesbian Collections (formerly the West Coast Lesbian Collections) made available to the public
August 1987 Connexxus Softball Team plays in the West Hollywood Women's Athletic League
October 1987 Connexxus East opens in El Centro Human Services Corporation in East Los Angeles
December 1987 Founders Lauren Jardine, Executive Director, and Del Martinez, Board President, retire from Connexxus. Pat Martel is elected new Board President.
March 1988 Five Plus Connexxus campaign begins.
May 1988 Denise Wheeler named new Executive Director.
May 19, 1988 Connexxus hosts "Courage to Heal: A presentation for Child Sexual Abuse Survivors" by Ellen Bass and Laura Davis.
October 1988 Connexxus moves to facility located at 1017 N. La Cienega Boulevard in West Hollywood.
October 1988 Cheryl Mendoza, Ph.D, is hired as new Clinical Director.
January 1989 Connexxus / Centro de Mujeres awarded Community Organization of the Year by Gay and Lesbian Latinos Unidos.
January 1989 The June Mazer Lesbian Collections move to 626 N. Robertson Boulevard in West Hollywood.
March 11, 1989 Connexxus and Southern California Women for Understanding co-sponsor "Passionate Politics: Lesbian-Feminism for the '90s" with feminist thinker and activist Charlotte Bunch.
April 1989 Wahneeta Pacheco named new Assistant Director
May 29, 1989 June Mazer Lesbian Collections Archivist Bunny MacCulloch passes away.
September 1989 Campaign SAVE CONNEXXUS! begins.
February 1990 Connexxus announces that it will be closing in June 1990.
February 1990 The Latina Lesbian Support Group announces their formal separation from Connexxus and Connexxus East.
June 1990 Connexxus closes.
Related Material
This collection forms part of the The June L. Mazer Archive at UCLA.
Online Version Available
Portions of this collection have been digitized and are available online: Connexxus/Centro de Mujeres Collection (409 items).
Connexxus (Center)
- Board of Directors, 1984-1991; Series 1.; 2 boxes, 1.5 linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  The Board of Directors series contains information related to the governance of Connexxus (Subseries 1: Policies), materials generated at Board retreats and meetings (Subseries 2: Retreats and Meetings), and minutes from each Board meeting (Subseries 3: Minutes). The material that is not part of these subseries includes to Board recruitment / nominating committee / membership, correspondence, fundraising, publicity, and the dissolution of Connexxus.
  Arrangement note
  The Board of Directors series is organized into three subseries - policies, retreats and meetings, and minutes. All other material that does not fall within these three subseries is organized alphabetically by folder title.
  - Applications, 1985-1989; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Contains application forms (blank), two submitted applications), activity record log (blank), committee descriptions, draft of Board member recruitment, selection and orientation process, and invitational letters from founders Lauren Jardine and Adel Martinez and Board President Pat Martel.
  - Contract, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Contains one copy of Board Roles and Responsibilities Contract labeled as a draft.
  - Correspondence, 1985, 1989; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Contains three pieces of inter-board correspondence from Lauren Jardine / Adel Martinez (founders), Carla Barboza (Board President), and Board member Ann Benvenuti. Includes a draft of assessment survey for Connexxus' programs and services.
  - Development Materials, 1985, 1988; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Contains articles and handouts on Board management, meetings, fundraising, and strategic planning. It is unclear if the Connexxus Board generated the handouts. With the exception of the magazine articles, the other materials have no date.
  - Dissolution Documents, 1990-1991; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Contains correspondence to and from lawyer including documents regarding assumption of liabilities, distribution of assets to Mazer Collection, certificate of dissolution, Board meeting minutes (12 December 1990), correspondence from CPA regarding a financial statement (30 April 1991) and tax returns (1990), financial documents, and other miscellaneous documentation.
  - Miscellaneous Materials, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Contains handwritten notes regarding Alliance / CBPWA, membership and programs committee members contact information, and storage of materials. No author or date listed for any of the documents.
  - Nominating Committee, 1986; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Contains welcome letter, applications (blank), handouts regarding Board recruitment and functions, member contributions (blank), 1986-1987 election ballot (blank), Nominating Committee report (9 June 1986), Board Structure Task Force report (20 November 1986), handwritten notes on nominating committee, board member criteria, and recruitment.
  - Organizational Structure, 1988; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Contains charts of organizational structure.
  - Publicity, 1985; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Contains Connexxus pamphlet draft, CBPWA program proposal, press release (n.d.), fact sheet, and business card draft.
  - Rosters, 1980, 1985-1988; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Member lists of Board of Directors
  - Policies, 1984-1989; Subseries 1.; 5 folders
    Folders are arranged alphabetically by title.
    Contains all documentation related to the governing of Connexxus.
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1984; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 9)
      General note
      3 copies.
    - Bylaws, 1984; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Financial Procedures Manual, n.d.; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Handbook, 1985-1986, 1988-1989; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Sections on Organizational Information, Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws, Financial Information, and Development. Formerly in folder labeled "Misc. Board Book Parts."
    - Miscellaneous, 1985; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 13)
      Contains information on Board member eligibility policy, draft of recommendations by the Professional Standards and Ethics Sub-Committee, statements regarding confidentiality and ethics, and advertising policy.
  - Retreats and Meetings, 1986-1991; Subseries 2.; 29 folders
    Folders are arranged chronologically.
    Contains materials generated at retreats and meetings - agendas, reports, minutes, budgets, and photographs.
    - Retreat (16-17 August 1986), 2 folders (Box 4, Folder 16 - 17)
      Folder 16: contains organizational information, articles of incorporation and bylaws, minutes (June - December 1985, January - September 1986), financial statements (November 1985), projected budget (July 1985 - June 1986, July 1986 - June 1987), board management worksheets.
      Folder 17: contains agenda, board member recruitment, selection and orientation draft, retreat planning logistics, organizational chart, list of Connexxus staff, proposed budget (July 1987 - June 1988), retreat summary / minutes, handwritten minutes, group photo of board members.
    - Retreat (22-23 August 1987), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 18)
      Contains agenda, fundraising presentation, retreat planning sheets, proposed budget, report to the Board on retreat's discussion of race, and photos of Board members at the retreat.
    - Retreat (20-21 August 1988), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 19)
      Contains agenda (draft and final).
    - Meeting (19 January 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 20)
      Contains agenda, Executive Director report (December 1988), various articles and letters on gender oppression (not authored by Connexxus), photocopied handwritten document on Connexxus mission.
    - Meeting (16 February 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 21)
      Contains agenda, minutes of January 1989 meeting, statement of income and expenses (January 1989), Executive Director report (January 1989), staff report (January 1989), Clinical Director report (January 1989), list of monthly tasks, Connexxus East staff report (January 1989).
    - Retreat (16 March 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 22)
      Contains agenda, statement of income and expenses (February 1989), minutes (16 February 1989), postcard invitation to "The World Around Me" photo exhibition by Laura Aguilar (postcard features photo of Board President Pat Martel).
    - Meeting (20 April 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Contains agenda, Executive Director report (March and April 1989), Assistant Director monthly report (April 1989), Clinical Director monthly report (March and April 1989), Connexxus East staff report (March and April 1989), staff report (March 1989), statement of income and expenses (February and March 1989), minutes (16 March 1989 and 15 December 1988 [amended and approved]), self assessment for City of West Hollywood, Social Services Midyear Program Evaluation (1988-1989), invitation to June L. Mazer Lesbian Collection fundraiser (7 May 1989?), and Project 10 correspondence.
    - Meeting (18 May 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 24)
      Contains agenda, Executive Director report (April 1989), Assistant Director monthly report (April 1989), Clinical Director monthly report (April 1989), Connexxus East staff report, statement of income and expenses (April 1989), correspondence regarding the softball team, City of West Hollywood Social Services contract extension memorandum.
    - Meeting (June 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 25)
      Contains minutes (20 April 1989), Executive Director monthly report (May 1989), Assistant Director monthly report (May 1989), Clinical Director monthly report (May 1989), correspondence from Carla Barboza to three board members regarding organizational racism and their resignations, correspondence regarding June L. Mazer Lesbian collection, copy of Bunny MacCulloch's obituary, resignation letters, submitted Board of Directors application.
    - Meeting (08 July 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 26)
      Formerly in folder labeled "July 8th, 27th, August 11th crisis meeting." Contains agenda (20 July 1989), memo from Pat Martel regarding task force on the future of Connexxus, materials on board functions and recruiting new members.
    - Meeting (20 July 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 27)
      Contains agenda, statement of income and expenses (July 1989), submitted board member application.
    - Meeting (17 August 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 28)
      Contains agenda, minutes (18 May 1989), Executive Director monthly report (June and July 1989), Assistant Director monthly report (June 1989), Clinical Director monthly report (June and July 1989), staff report (May and June 1989), City of West Hollywood Social Services monthly report, memo from Pat Martel on task force and the future of Connexxus (1 August 1989), list of City of West Hollywood expenditures, correspondence and recommendations with CPAs regarding Connexxus' financial status.
    - Retreat (August 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 29)
      Contains documents relating to the planning of the August 1989 retreat.
    - Meeting (21 September 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 30)
      Contains agenda, minutes (17 August 1989, 5 September 1989), Executive Director monthly report (August 1989), correspondence from City of West Hollywood regarding future of Connexxus.
    - Meeting (19 October 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 31)
      Contains agenda, meeting (21 September 1989, 27 September 1989, 19 October 1989), and statement of income and expenses (March 1989).
    - Meeting (16 November 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 32)
      Contains agenda, submitted board applications, handwritten financial notes.
    - Meeting (27 December 1989), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 33)
      Contains statement of income and expenses (November 1989) and cash flow projections (1990).
    - Meeting (17 January 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 34)
      Contains agenda (handwritten), minutes (27 December 1989, 3 January 1990, 17 January 1990), statement of income and expenses (December 1989), June L. Mazer Collection financial statement, letter to community regarding the closure of Connexxus (18 January 1990), Connexxus Begins Rite of Passage document, Connexxus task force recommendations, check registers.
    - Meeting (February 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 35)
      Contains minutes (17 January 1990), correspondence from the Latina Lesbian Support Group regarding the closure of Connexxus, Connexxus' letter to the community printed in the Lesbian News, income and expenses report (January 1990), June L. Mazer Lesbian Collection financial statement (March 1987 - December 1989), Interim Coordinator report (21 February 1990, handwritten), Connexxus East's list of concerns (31 January 1989, handwritten).
    - Meeting (21 March 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 36)
      Contains agenda, minutes (21 February 1990, 21 March 1990), board member letter of resignation, Alliance Steering Committee agenda (7 March 1990), budget and attendance report (January and February 1990), minutes (11 February 1990), recommended procedures and policies regarding Connexxus closure and the counseling program by Nicki Toomey and Lauree Moss, event listing, income and expense report (January and February 1990), correspondence from Latina Lesbian Support Group regarding the termination of its relationship with Connexxus.
    - Meeting (18 April 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 37)
      Contains agenda, minutes (21 March 1990), income and expense report (March 1990), Alliance income and expense report (October 1989 - March 1990), cash flow projections (revised 1990).
    - Meeting (16 May 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 38)
      Contains agenda, income and expenses report (April 1990), confidential draft of recommendations made to Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center /GLCSC (7 May 1990).
    - Meeting (28 June 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 39)
      Contains agenda, minutes (16 May 1990), list of bank account signators, statement of income and expenses (May 1990), Connexxus "Coming Out" Hotline report, June Mazer Lesbian Collection financial statement (March - December 1989), expenses (January - June 1990), budget (July 1990 - June 1991), Alliance income and expenses report, budget (July 1990 - June 1991), handwritten financial notes regarding July salaries and vacations.
    - Meeting (16 July 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 40)
      Contains agenda, statement of financial condition (June 1990), statement of income and expenses (June 1990).
    - Meeting (17 October 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 41)
      Contains agenda, minutes (18 April 1990, 28 June 1990), Board of Directors roster, Connexxus operating budget (fiscal year 1991), softball invitation, statement of financial condition (30 September 1990), statement of income and expenses (30 September 1990), insurance coverage (fiscal year 1991).
    - Meeting (18 November 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 42)
      Contains statement of financial condition (October 1990), statement of income and expenses (October 1990).
    - Meeting (12 December 1990), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 43)
      Contains statement of financial condition (November 1990), statement of income and expenses (November 1990).
    - Meeting (January 1991), 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Contains statement of financial condition (December 1990), statement of income and expenses (December 1990).
  - Minutes, 1985-1990; Subseries 3.; 7 folders
    Contains minutes from meetings and retreats.
    - 1985, June - December 1985; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
      2 sets
    - 1986, January - July, September - December 1986; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1987, January - July, September - December 1987; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
      2 sets. Second set consists only of January through June 1987.
    - 1988, January - July, September - December 1988; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
      2 sets. Second set missing August and December.
    - 1989, January - May, July - December 1989; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
      2 sets.
    - 1990, January - July, October - December 1990; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
      Includes letter to the community and proof report which is inaccurately dated as 1980 and should be 1990.
- Administrative Files, Series 2.; 3 boxes
  - Connexxus Collection Inventory, n.d.; 6 folders (Box 3, Folder 1 - 5, 21)
    Inventory generated by June L. Mazer Lesbian Archives
  - Human Resources, 1985-1990; Subseries 1.; 22 folders
    Folders are arranged alphabetically.
    Contains forms, job descriptions, applications, and personnel files. Personnel files are restricted until the year 2014.
    - Forms, 1986-1987; 5 folders (Box 1, Folder 37 - 41)
      Folder 41: Assistant Director Application (1987)
      Folder 37: Confidentiality Statement (n.d.)
      Folder 38: Conflict Resolution (n.d.)
      Folder 39: Ethics Statement (n.d)
      Folder 40: Performance Evaluation (1986)
    - General, 1987-1989; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Contains job postings, blank time sheet, budget request, and one denied application.
    - Unemployment, 1990; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Worker's Compensation, 1991; 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Applicants, 1985, 1987-1988; 3 folders (Box 2, Folder 1, 14 - 15)
      Folder 1: Clinical Director (1988)
      Folder 14: Executive Director (1988)
      Folder 15: Latina Services Coordinator (1985, 1987)
      Restricted until 2014.
    - Employees, 1985-1989; 11 folders (Box 2, Folder 2 - 13)
      Folder 2: Alquijay, Marta (1987)
      Folder 3: Blaiwes, Robin (1989)
      Folder 4: Friedman, Mona (1985-1989)
      Folder 5: Gonzales, Stella (1986-1988)
      Folder 6: Jacobs, Leslie (1989)
      Folder 7: Jardine, Lauren (1985-1987)
      Folder 8: Levy, Sharon M. (1989)
      Folder 9: McTeague, Maureen (1985, 1988)
      Folder 10: Mendoza, Cheryl (1988-1989)
      Folder 11: Morrow, Judy (1988)
      Folder 12: Morton, Gini (1988-1989)
      Folder 13: Pullen, Suzanne (1989)